<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep Ecology - Education</title><link href="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/feeds/category/education.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.byronjsmith.com/</id><updated>2017-01-01T18:30:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Teaching Python by the (Note)Book</title><link href="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/python-lesson-balance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-01T18:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-01T18:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:blog.byronjsmith.com,2017-01-01:/python-lesson-balance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr:&lt;/strong&gt; I tried out a &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/bsmith89/5eeb9e7da35bd6b8bf28ae884f6478ff"&gt;modified Python lesson&lt;/a&gt;
and I think it was successful at balancing learner motivation with teaching
foundational (and sometimes boring) concepts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, &lt;a href="https://software-carpentry.org"&gt;teaching Python to scientists&lt;/a&gt;
is easier than just about every other audience.
The learning objective is clear: write code to make my science more accurate,
more efficient, and more impactful.
The motivation is apparent: data is increasingly plentiful and increasingly
complex.
The learners are both engaged and prepared to put in the effort
required to develop new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, despite all of the advantages, teaching &lt;em&gt;anybody&lt;/em&gt; to program is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, one of the most challenging trade-offs for lesson planners
is between motivating the material and teaching a mental model
for code execution.
For example, scientists are easily motivated by simple data munging and
plotting using &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt;;
these are features of the Python ecosystem that can convince …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr:&lt;/strong&gt; I tried out a &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/bsmith89/5eeb9e7da35bd6b8bf28ae884f6478ff"&gt;modified Python lesson&lt;/a&gt;
and I think it was successful at balancing learner motivation with teaching
foundational (and sometimes boring) concepts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, &lt;a href="https://software-carpentry.org"&gt;teaching Python to scientists&lt;/a&gt;
is easier than just about every other audience.
The learning objective is clear: write code to make my science more accurate,
more efficient, and more impactful.
The motivation is apparent: data is increasingly plentiful and increasingly
complex.
The learners are both engaged and prepared to put in the effort
required to develop new skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, despite all of the advantages, teaching &lt;em&gt;anybody&lt;/em&gt; to program is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, one of the most challenging trade-offs for lesson planners
is between motivating the material and teaching a mental model
for code execution.
For example, scientists are easily motivated by simple data munging and
plotting using &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt;;
these are features of the Python ecosystem that can convince a graduate
student to pay attention to the material instead of answering emails.
Actually &lt;em&gt;using&lt;/em&gt; these features, however, requires a long list of basic
concepts: Python syntax, libraries, function calls, objects and methods,
conditionals, and variable assignment, to name just a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lesson planner can start from the basics, working in to these features
along the branches of the dependency tree, but that could require hours
(or even days) of "boring programming".
It's all too easy to dismiss learners who lose interest before you get
to the good stuff, but it is more a reflection of the materials and
instructor, than the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the other extreme, a lesson could start with working code,
or, in the Software Carpentry style the instructor could lead learners
through writing code that uses these features, before the concepts have
been fully introduced.
This in-at-the-deep-end approach quickly demonstrates exciting uses of Python,
but at the risk of intimidating learners, making them wonder if they're the
only one in the room who's confused by what's going on under the hood and what
all of the syntax means.
I'm not aware of any studies on this topic (if you are, please pass them my
way), but I'm willing to speculate that this second approach has
a higher risk of subjecting learners from underrepresented groups to stereotype
threat, a major risk when teaching a subject with a pervasive diversity
problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us all, there's a whole spectrum of approaches in between the
motivations-first and foundations-first extremes.
We can trust learners to self-motivate for a time, especially when we're
teaching scientists.
Attendees are there voluntarily (I would hope).
Likewise, learners will never have a perfect understanding of how their code is
working, regardless of how long you spend teaching the basics.
The key is to avoid unintentionally teaching pathological mental models that
are difficult for the instructor to diagnose and iterate beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;State of the Python lesson&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, the current default Python lesson for Software Carpentry is
&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/"&gt;"Novice Inflammation"&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref-inflammation-commit"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-inflammation-commit"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
I have &lt;a href="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/swc-python-lesson.html"&gt;written previously&lt;/a&gt; about my experience
with the lesson, and have not been shy with my criticism.
There is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; to be positive about in the composition of Inflammation.
It has been an effective approach to teaching Python to what at this point
must be several thousand workshop attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this post is about how we can do better.
My primary criticism focuses on the first section:
&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/01-numpy/"&gt;"Analyzing Patient Data"&lt;/a&gt;.
The approach here falls towards the motivation-first extreme.
Learners are shown how one might go from raw data in a CSV to heatmaps
and line plots, two useful skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside, however, is that this happens without fully explaining the
syntax, what libraries are, &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; arrays versus Python lists, &lt;code&gt;dtypes&lt;/code&gt; vs
built-in Python types, and more.
I think that by using this particular motivating example while glossing over
those details we're giving learners a challenging mental model to iterate
beyond.
What's more, I believe that this results in a &lt;em&gt;diversity&lt;/em&gt; of models
making later instruction more likely to leave some learners behind.
Novice Inflammation also gets stuck in the weeds over difficult concepts which,
in my opinion, aren't nearly as important for learners, for example,
accumulating over particular axes in &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this and other reasons Greg Wilson spearheaded an attempt to
reinvent the Python lesson.
The &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-gapminder/"&gt;"Novice Gapminder" lesson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref-gapminder-commit"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-gapminder-commit"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
is a from-scratch re-write.
It's worth noting that SWC's normal pull-request model for lesson development
is unable to accommodate a major overhaul like this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gapminder is different in several ways, for instance using &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; as a focal
library instead of &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;.
Notably for this commentary, though, it also takes a much more gradual approach
to motivating the material.
&lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; are not introduced until the end of the first
half-day,
and only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; a thorough discussion of variable assignment, functions, and
data types.
The Gapminder lesson also appears to lack the distractions and rabbit holes
that I've criticized in Inflammation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think Gapminder hits a superior balance between motivation
and basics, while also improve the structure and refining the details.
I have to applaud everyone who's contributed to its development.
I've now taught from the new lesson once, and co-instructed a workshop that
used the first half.
The improvements in the design were apparent both times.
I expect it to be well received by the SWC community when it becomes the
default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Continual improvement&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to say, however, that it cannot be improved.
The same motivation-vs-foundations question has already come up in
&lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/python-novice-gapminder/issues/113"&gt;a discussion on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.
A proposal was made to delay the use of &lt;code&gt;pandas&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; until the
second half, further front-loading the basics.
My personal opinion, having taught the lesson is that
this is unnecessary.
With the Gapminder lesson, by the time we got to these more advanced topics at
the end of the first half-day, learners appeared to be ready for the material,
comfortably updating their mental models in an appropriate way.
And, thankfully, I also didn't notice a loss of engagement due to the delayed
pay-off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many trade-offs in lesson design, the optimal position on the
motivations/foundations spectrum is context dependent.
I would focus on cool application instead of basic concepts
for the first session if I were
teaching high school students or any learners skeptical about the utility of
the material.
A room full of scientists who were there specifically to learn Python, however,
could probably tolerate even more front-loading of syntax and control-flow.
A framework to help instructors customize the materials for their audience
would be a very useful addition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main purpose of this post is to nominate a slightly different approach
which introduces an advanced example early in the lesson without the
risk (I believe) of intimidating learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2016 I co-instructed a (not officially SWC)
&lt;a href="https://umswc.github.io/2016-12-14-umich/"&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; which taught Python over two half-day sessions to
about 20 learners, primarily graduate students in the biological sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My co-instructor, Jackie Cohen (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jczetta"&gt;\@jczetta&lt;/a&gt;),
taught the first half-day using the Gapminder lesson.
The positive reception from learners to the first half of the material was
testament not only to her skillful instruction, but also the quality of the
design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then taught the second day with the
same gapminder dataset and covering the same
topics as the normal materials, but using &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/bsmith89/5eeb9e7da35bd6b8bf28ae884f6478ff"&gt;a custom lesson plan&lt;/a&gt;.
Inspired by &lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/python-novice-gapminder/issues/113#issuecomment-256230540"&gt;a comment&lt;/a&gt; on the Gapminder GitHub repository,
I constructed a "realistic" analysis of the gapminder data
as a Jupyter notebook.
In particular, the notebook includes code to generate a fairly involved
figure telling a story about the relationship between per-capita GDP and
life-expectancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An example visualization of the gapminder data." src="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/static/images/gapminder-analysis.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started the second day by having learners download and run this notebook,
demonstrating the quality of analyses they could produce with fewer than 100
lines of code.
By &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; live-coding, and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; expecting the learners to type along during the
introduction, I believe this approach minimizes the likelihood of intimidating
the learners with syntax.
To that end, I also did not walk through the code itself, but instead focused
on describing the overarching flow of the analysis:
loading external data, selecting a subset, plotting two columns as a
scatter-plot with a third column determining the size of the points, running a
linear regression, and plotting a best-fit line.
The purpose of this introduction was purely to motivate the material, not
to introduce the concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then had them open a new, empty notebook, and the remainder of the lesson
(which &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; done in the traditional live-coding style)
then revolved around reconstructing the same analysis from scratch,
a thematic unification, that I found to be elegant.
Since the pre-constructed analysis made use of for-loops, if-statements,
and functions, I was able to limit my use of foo/bar style examples and
quickly return to the core analysis demonstrating the use of these elements
in a realistic setting.
Our workshop was advertised as an introduction to Jupyter notebooks, data
manipulation, and plotting, (as well as novice Python) so a significant
fraction of the time was spent on these topics and libraries instead of more
foundational concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Where to go from here?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this approach to be quite successful.
In-person and exit survey feedback has been uniformly positive and
learners appeared to have achieved most or all of the learning objectives
of the core Gapminder lesson.
While the "realistic analysis" approach sounds more like the
&lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;
style, in this particular case it was a great fit for the Software Carpentry
learning objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that this model could be implemented in the core Gapminder lesson,
perhaps starting in the second half (as we did), or with a different
example notebook for each half-day.
That would, however, entail modifying most or all of the sections to
focus on the new unified example.
Is it worth expending the tens of hours required to implement it?
Even if it were implemented, I'm not convinced that the SWC lesson development
model makes this kind of large-scale refactoring feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative to submitting a pull request,
I'm hoping that I can convince a few instructors to try it out for themselves.
Positive experiences with an unofficial fork makes patching the main branch a
more rational investment.
I've already been &lt;a href="http://lists.software-carpentry.org/pipermail/discuss/2016-May/004529.html"&gt;evangelizing&lt;/a&gt; in a similar way for an
&lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/git-novice-outline"&gt;alternative Git lesson&lt;/a&gt;,
sharing my immature outline and encouraging folks to try it out
themselves.
Is there a better approach to making medium to large changes to the design of
a SWC lesson?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion: I think we need additional discussion (and data) about the
motivations/foundations trade-off in our lessons.
I'd also like to hear your thoughts on the best way to lobby for and introduce
moderately sized changes to the core materials.
What do you think about my approach?
If you're feeling brave, please try it out and let me know how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-inflammation-commit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HEAD at
&lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/python-novice-inflammation/tree/030f3fbd3006cea06e42bbd14a62ddb33098b9f6"&gt;030f3fbd30&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-inflammation-commit" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-gapminder-commit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HEAD at &lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/python-novice-gapminder/tree/e303e6a9d309bdcbcfb370c8125b7792d4096968"&gt;e303e6a9d3&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-gapminder-commit" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="software-carpentry"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="programming"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="jupyter"></category></entry><entry><title>First time teaching Python to novices</title><link href="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/swc-python-lesson.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-12T01:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-08-14T10:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:blog.byronjsmith.com,2015-08-12:/swc-python-lesson.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This July I co-instructed with &lt;a href="https://impactstory.org/JenniferShelton"&gt;Jennifer Shelton&lt;/a&gt;
a Software Carpentry &lt;a href="http://i5k-kinbre-script-share.github.io/2015-07-23-stanford/"&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; at Stanford University,
targeted to researchers with genomic or evolutionary datasets.
Jennifer taught the shell (Bash) and version control with Git,
while I taught the general programming language Python.
I've been aware of the &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;organization&lt;/a&gt;, which teaches software
development and computational methods to scientists, since attending a
workshop in 2012.
Since then I've served as a helper at one workshop
(troubleshooting individual learner's problems and helping catch them up with
the rest of the class),
and gone through the "accelerated", two day, instructor training at Michigan
State University.
After the Stanford workshop, I took part in new-instructor debriefing
on August 4th, during which I mentioned that I had to greatly pare down the
community-written lesson plan, &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/"&gt;python-novice-inflammation&lt;/a&gt;,
to fit into the two half-day session we allotted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karin and Tiffany, who were running the debriefing, asked me to send …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This July I co-instructed with &lt;a href="https://impactstory.org/JenniferShelton"&gt;Jennifer Shelton&lt;/a&gt;
a Software Carpentry &lt;a href="http://i5k-kinbre-script-share.github.io/2015-07-23-stanford/"&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; at Stanford University,
targeted to researchers with genomic or evolutionary datasets.
Jennifer taught the shell (Bash) and version control with Git,
while I taught the general programming language Python.
I've been aware of the &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;organization&lt;/a&gt;, which teaches software
development and computational methods to scientists, since attending a
workshop in 2012.
Since then I've served as a helper at one workshop
(troubleshooting individual learner's problems and helping catch them up with
the rest of the class),
and gone through the "accelerated", two day, instructor training at Michigan
State University.
After the Stanford workshop, I took part in new-instructor debriefing
on August 4th, during which I mentioned that I had to greatly pare down the
community-written lesson plan, &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/"&gt;python-novice-inflammation&lt;/a&gt;,
to fit into the two half-day session we allotted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karin and Tiffany, who were running the debriefing, asked me to send a note
to the mentorship email list about which parts I removed and which I kept in.
I thought I'd also take the opportunity to comment on the material at large:
what worked for me and what didn't.
What started as an email quickly ballooned into this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be explicit, I was teaching from the state of the repository at the time of
the workshop&lt;sup id="fnref-repo-state"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-repo-state"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this as my first workshop&lt;sup id="fnref-unprepared"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-unprepared"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I (incorrectly) thought
I could teach all of the topics straight through.
By the time it became apparent that this wasn't going to work,
adapting the first day's material had to be done on the fly.
After that experience, and
before the following afternoon,
I prepared a subset of the remaining material that I thought I could cover.
I'm now relying on my (somewhat traumatic) memory of the first session,
and that outline I put together for the second day to write this summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan going in was to split &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/index.html#topics"&gt;the material&lt;/a&gt; after Topic 6,
getting learners up to writing functions on the first day,
so that we could discuss debugging and best-practices,
and transition from the Jupyter notebook to shell scripts, the next day.
Based on my co-instructors recommendation,
I did not have learners do all of the challenge questions for each topic,
but instead picked just one or two that I thought would be most useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found myself wishing (especially for Topic 1: "Analyzing Patient Data") that
some of the easier questions were integrated into the lesson itself, instead of
all at the bottom.
Learners should have had more chances to problem-solve early, instead of
listening to me for the entirety of each topic before getting their feet wet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Motivating Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For that &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/01-numpy.html"&gt;first topic&lt;/a&gt; I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; cover everything, but wish I hadn't,
since it was mostly focused on array operations and the specifics of working
with NumPy (e.g. operations along axes).
I appreciated that we were showing the learners powerful library features to
motivate the later work, but I didn't feel like it was great for this
workshop's "genomics" audience.
Maybe these initial motivating sections should be targeted the same way the
capstone projects are.
It was also too long relative to the other sections, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; very good, however, for introducing some python specifics, especially
things that learners coming from other languages like R or Mathematica might
not know (e.g. 0-indexing, slices, that variable assignment happens when each
line is executed, etc.).
It gave learners a chance to be surprised by their misconceptions and ask
questions.
We should do more of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have been helpful for the lesson to have pre-built explanations for
0-indexing and right-exclusive slicing, since these were the hard parts and I'm
not happy with the explanations I initially used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the nature of the made-up data (maximum values smooth and minimum
values as a step-function along the first axis) distracting.
I also didn't know what they were supposed to represent (beyond inflammation
over time), so the "actually doing science" part of the motivation was a bit
lost.
Is there a reason we use these data?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Python basics: lists, loops, conditionals, etc.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/02-loop.html"&gt;Topics 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/03-lists.html"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, "Repeating Actions with Loops" and
"Storing Multiple Values in Lists" respectively, were good and short.
I didn't feel like I had to cut anything out.
However, for-loop syntax was not explicitly covered early in the lesson plan.
It wasn't until I realized I had gotten ahead of myself that we talked about
loop variables, iterables&lt;sup id="fnref-iterables"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-iterables"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and the indented code-block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also thought the segue from Topic 1 to 2 was a bit weak.
This was a theme throughout, mixing the inflammation data with much simpler
stuff (e.g. looping over short strings and lists).
I realize we want to keep the motivation going, but, as a first-time
instructor, I found it to be distracting, and didn't know which I should be
emphasizing to the learners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also picked the wrong challenge question from Topic 1 (reverse &lt;code&gt;'Newton'&lt;/code&gt;
using a loop), since we hadn't covered &lt;code&gt;range&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;append&lt;/code&gt;ing to lists,
&lt;code&gt;''.join&lt;/code&gt;, etc.
What novice audience is that question appropriate for?
Maybe the solution is simple and I'm just confused...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material for &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/04-files.html"&gt;topic 4&lt;/a&gt;, "Analyzing Data from Multiple Files"
worked well overall.
The only mistake I remember was copy-pasting the big chunk of code from the
lesson (looping over files and drawing sets of plots) instead of typing it out.
I figured since most of the code was library calls, learners wouldn't get
anything out of me taking the time to type all of it.
That may have been true, but it meant the learners weren't executing the code
at the
same time as me, which interrupted the flow of the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/05-cond.html"&gt;Topic 5&lt;/a&gt;, "Making Choice" (if-statements), was where things got
hairy.
I panicked a bit and went mostly off the lesson plan.
It did not go well.
When I tried to find something in the lesson to get me back on track,
I wished there was more explicit discussion of syntax and booleans.
I was able to review the topic the next day, which I think got any lost
learners
mostly caught up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, at this point we were nearing the end of the first day.
I did manage to show the learners the syntax for defining and using functions,
but I covered &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/06-func.html"&gt;topic 6&lt;/a&gt;, "Creating Functions", in its entirety at the
start of the next
session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning my lesson&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the harrowing experience with conditionals on the first day, I took the
time to write out a personalized lesson outline for the next day with learning
objectives, steps in explaining difficult concepts, and pre-picked
understanding/challenge questions.
The exercise of writing an outline of learning objectives before the class was
very helpful, and something I intend to repeat before future workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I remember correctly&lt;sup id="fnref-metamemory"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-metamemory"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the second day I started once again with
functions, and largely based the lesson on the material in
&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/06-func.html"&gt;the topic&lt;/a&gt;.
The temperature conversion formulas were an effective motivator for this
lesson.
I wonder if simple examples, like this one, can replace the more complex
(and, admittedly, more impressive)
inflammation tutorial to demonstrate the value of Python for scientists.
I also integrated material from the &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/07-errors.html"&gt;topic on errors and exceptions&lt;/a&gt;:
tracebacks, syntax errors, etc.
In this combined topic I did not use the &lt;code&gt;import errors_01&lt;/code&gt; example.
It was unclear to me why the lesson plan, as written, uses a black-box script
like &lt;code&gt;errors_01.py&lt;/code&gt;, and not something more explicit, like an index or
attribute error, to dissect the traceback.
I think the explicit approach worked well for the learners in this workshop.
Since we were covering functions anyway, it wasn't hard to get a multi-level
traceback.
Syntax errors also combined nicely with learning function definition syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The author dissecting an attribute error.5" src="https://blog.byronjsmith.com/static/images/swc-stanford-byron.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the process of talking about functions we got sidetracked with
&lt;code&gt;open()&lt;/code&gt;.
I was surprised to see that the lesson plans have only limited discussion of
file objects, only really dealing with them in the section on &lt;code&gt;IOErrors&lt;/code&gt;.
I think learners appreciated a chance to see how the array data they had used
the day before were saved as a CSV,
and how they could access the data directly.
It also gave us a chance to show that other objects besides lists and strings
can serve as iterators in for-loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked how the topic 6 &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/06-func.html#defining-defaults"&gt;lesson plan&lt;/a&gt; used the library
function &lt;code&gt;numpy.loadtxt()&lt;/code&gt; to talk about default arguments and the &lt;code&gt;help()&lt;/code&gt;
built-in.
I jumped back and forth between examining that function and implementing
the same things (keywords, documentation) in a &lt;code&gt;center()&lt;/code&gt; function we were
building.
The realized lesson was very similar to the repository's lesson plan,
but a little more integrated with errors and exceptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the learners implement &lt;code&gt;rescale()&lt;/code&gt; as a challenge question.
We then worked together as a class to add lower and upper bounds.
This was a much more difficult task than I expected
(even just deriving the correct formula),
and served nicely to demonstrate defensive programming and debugging.
While we touched on many of the concepts in &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/08-defensive.html"&gt;topics 8&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/09-debugging.html"&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;,
these ideas, were spread throughout,
and I did not walk through either as an atomic lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ultimate goal on the second day was to write a program to calculate
the mean inflammation of each subject in the example files and then
transform the program into a command-line script that would operate as a
UNIX-style filter.
I remember Greg Wilson teaching Python scripting (along with Bash and SQL)
that way during my first workshop (as a &lt;em&gt;learner&lt;/em&gt;!) at MSU
in May 2012&lt;sup id="fnref-swc-msu"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn-swc-msu"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
This &lt;a href="http://swcarpentry.github.io/python-novice-inflammation/10-cmdline.html"&gt;last topic&lt;/a&gt; seemed like a worthwhile mini-capstone,
since it would reintroduce ideas from the Bash lesson the day before,
and we could version-control our work with git.
While we managed to run our code as a script (rather than a cell in the
Jupyter notebook), the transition was a little rough around the edges, and we
didn't have time to add &lt;code&gt;sys.argv&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;sys.stdin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Take-aways&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second day of Python was much smoother than the first, and, while we
did not get to all of the material, I was satisfied with what we did cover.
It's quite remarkable that learners can go all the way from indexing into lists
to defensive programming and unit tests in just a few hours.
I'm not convinced that we got them far enough to jump right into using Python
for their own work, but I hope it was a good kick-start towards that goal.
I'm amazed some novice workshops only allocate a half-day session to the
programming language (be it Python, R, or Matlab),
although a quick survey of &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/workshops/index.html#future"&gt;upcoming workshops&lt;/a&gt; suggests that almost
&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them do in fact use two sessions.
Is this the recommended approach (and if so where is it documented)
or have many instructors all independently come to the same conclusion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, there's still more material in python-novice-inflammation
than can be covered in two sessions.
I'm under the impression that the repository is sort of &lt;em&gt;meant&lt;/em&gt; to be like
that: way too big, so that instructors can pick and choose the parts that are
most salient for their audience.
This seems like a good idea, but
it was not sufficiently communicated to me as a first-time instructor,
and, while many of the difficulties I had could have been solved with more
comprehensive preparation,
having a "default" subset would have been helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-repo-state"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/swcarpentry/python-novice-inflammation/tree/76e3ea24406e4b8d684c9b45f3c5fd33e23ac71a"&gt;&lt;code&gt;76e3ea24406e4b8d684c9b45f3c5fd33e23ac71a&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: still the
HEAD as of this writing.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-repo-state" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-unprepared"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and being insufficiently prepared&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-unprepared" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-iterables"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, we talked about getting values from lists and how
strings are like lists, rather than about iterables in general.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-iterables" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-metamemory"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that I have those notes, I actually don't
remember the details of that day's lesson as well.
I wonder if there's some weird metamemory thing going on
e.g. &lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/333/6043/776.abstract"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; (unfortunately paywalled).&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-metamemory" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-photo-credit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo credit: Amy Hodge (&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"&gt;CC-BY&lt;/a&gt;)&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-photo-credit" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-swc-msu"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site for this historic event can still be found
&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120514195748/http://software-carpentry.org/boot-camps/michigan-state-university-may-2012/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref-swc-msu" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="software-carpentry"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="programming"></category><category term="mistakes"></category><category term="python"></category></entry></feed>