<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep Ecology</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/feeds/byron-j-smith.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2015-08-02T11:08:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>This is a Test</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/test.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-08-02T11:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2015-08-02:blog/test.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;TEST TEST TEST&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="microbiology"></category><category term="cheaters"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="pathogens"></category></entry><entry><title>Do Bacterial Species Exist?</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/microbial-species.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-06T18:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-08-06:blog/microbial-species.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Any of my friends or colleagues who have had the &amp;quot;pleasure&amp;quot; of talking about science with me for more than a few hours know that I am prepared, at the drop of a hat, to rant extensively about several standing debates in biology which I consider merely semantic. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q&lt;/strong&gt;: Are viruses alive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Who CARES!?&lt;/em&gt; Viruses do what they do. Cellular organisms do something else. What difference does it make if we decide to allow our middle-schoolers to draw little dotted lines around animals, bacteria, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; viruses? And I don't even want to &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; the word &amp;quot;prion&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a similar level of disdain for people who try to decide on a single definition for &amp;quot;species&amp;quot;. Ultimately I am a pluralist: the definition should be tailored to the scientific question. Paleontologists, you have your morphological species concept, because what &lt;em&gt;else&lt;/em&gt; do stony fossils allow? Are you studying speciation, you can keep the biological species concept, just be prepared for the inevitable craziness when fairly divergent plants hybridize or genes are transferred horizontally. Macro-evolution folks, don't give up on the phylogenetic species concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, I have no tolerance for arbitrary definitions which do not admit to their arbitrariness. Since I have yet to be convinced otherwise, this has precluded my acceptance of higher taxonomic divisions. If someone can give me a non-arbitrary definition for genus, order, family, phylum, etc. I would love to know what it is. As far as I am concerned they're just a naming system for monophyletic groups which pander to dead systematists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="most-species-concepts-are-not-applicable-or-arbitrary"&gt;Most species concepts are not applicable or arbitrary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us microbiologists, several &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.micro.56.012302.160634"&gt;species concepts&lt;/a&gt; are in use. The genetic species concept groups organisms whose full genomes or selected genes have diverged minimally. This definition is applied in operational taxonomic unit (OTU) based analysis, and indirectly in whole genome DNA-DNA hybridization, the traditional determination of bacterial species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OTU thresholds are certainly arbitrary; The definition fully acknowledges that fact. But the OTU concept is particularly useful for culture independent methods, since genetic distance is perhaps the only measure of familial resemblance available. Just as the biological species concept doesn't do much good for a paleontologist who lacks live, mating specimens, a morphological species concept is helpless when faced with sequence divorced from physiology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When in possession of pure cultures, however, and therefore the luxury of phenotypic data, a physiological (which I'm using synonymously with &amp;quot;morphological&amp;quot;) species concept is viable. Unfortunately, application of the morphogical definition depends critically on the exhaustivity of our search for physiological differences and an arbitrary delineation between groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phylogenetic species concept is equally impotent. I challenge the reader to devise a monophyletic &amp;quot;basic unit&amp;quot; for any &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asexual_reproduction"&gt;agamogenic&lt;/a&gt; organism which does not classify every daughter as a new species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the lack of canonical sex in microbes, an unsurprising (if not justifiable) urge to model ourselves after animal ecologists has driven some microbiologists to consider a biological species concept as well. With many microbes partaking in some form of recombination through transduction, transformation, or conjugation, it seems feasible to group those individuals which are capable of exchanging genetic material into a single species. Unfortunately this definition leaves behind all those clades which are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; known to horizontally transfer genes. What's more, it fails the &amp;quot;arbitrariness test&amp;quot;: how much recombination is required before two individuals share a species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ecological-species-concept-saves-the-day"&gt;The ecological species concept saves the day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if everything else is ultimately arbitrary, what's left? Originally formulated by Leigh Van Valen (&lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/1219444"&gt;1976&lt;/a&gt;), the ecological species concept has been distilled down to (&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1420-9101.2009.01897.x"&gt;Martinez-Gordillo, 2010&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A species is a set of [related] organisms exploiting (or adapted to) a single niche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that's interesting! The ecological concept flips the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Competitive_exclusion_principle"&gt;competitive exclusion principle&lt;/a&gt; upside down. This definition sets the threshold for familial resemblance at the point where two lineages are no longer in the same niche. While there are still some rough edges, namely questions about what constitutes a niche, this definition appears to pass the test of arbitrariness and makes a satisfying connection between taxonomy and ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their inherent differences in criteria, and in my opinion defensibility, all of these species concepts (genetic, morphological, biological, and ecological) are getting at the same core idea: what makes one organism more &amp;quot;like&amp;quot; another? What keeps the diversity of life clumped together into identifiable units? There is a certain harmony to these species concepts. Whether &lt;strong&gt;recombination&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;ecological&lt;/strong&gt; processes, we expect the end result to be &lt;strong&gt;genetic&lt;/strong&gt; similarity which will manifest itself as &lt;strong&gt;physiological&lt;/strong&gt; clustering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="are-species-empirically-real"&gt;Are species empirically real?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait. This is certainly begging the question. Does the microbial world &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; have this assumed genetic and physiological clustering? Finally, a hypothesis to be tested!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanage &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt; have (&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098%2Frstb.2006.1917"&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt;) summarized the current literature on genomic clustering and, in a second paper (&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1159388"&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;), the models which may explain the observations. The data is somewhat ambiguous. &lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; from the 2009 paper demonstrates several of the problems facing an empirically described microbial species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/323/5915/741/F1.expansion.html"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;img src="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/323/5915/741/F1.large.jpg"
     alt="Two examples exhibiting conflicts with species concepts in microbes."
     class="full-width"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, and most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;1A&lt;/strong&gt; shows that genetic distance between and within clusters of &lt;em&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/em&gt; isolates is not consistent. Current species designations are indicated. Clearly, the level of genetic distance within any visually (indicated by terminal node color) or &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; designated species varies by a factor of 5 or more. What's more, &lt;strong&gt;1B&lt;/strong&gt; demonstrates that while ecological preference (terminal node color) is fairly correlated with phylogeny in &lt;em&gt;Vibrio&lt;/em&gt;, some clades lack this association, specifically &lt;em&gt;V. splendidus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fractal-like clustering in the &lt;em&gt;Streptococcus&lt;/em&gt; phylogeny makes me wonder if we're not seeing the result of numerous intense bottlenecks or selective sweeps which occur stochastically. And, while the ecological-phylogenetic mapping is fairly consistent, a point in favor of the species concept, I am curious if stabilizing selection and/or recombination models explain this clustering better than other, less interesting processes (e.g. gradual niche migration). I'm also concerned about problems with sampling. If there were genotypes which bridged the clusters would we know it? And, like every database dependent analysis in microbiology, a bias for pathogens could be misleading us here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so..."&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Betteridge&amp;#39;s_law_of_headlines"&gt;So...&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a exhaustive debate over the semantics of asexual species, surprisingly little data has has been collected to show that bacteria even exhibit more than trivial clustering. Several mechanisms have been proposed for maintaining genetic conformity, namely recombination and niche specificity. Some of this research has aimed to find parallels with plant and animal ecology, but I would suggest we lose little by discarding the species concept entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can understand the need to define morpho-species when diagnosing disease, or the utility of OTU based approaches in molecular surveys. I'm also not suggesting that we should stop categorizing strains into species; the convenience for communicating microbiology is undeniable. But by remembering that most species divisions are arbitrary, and that every microbe is a new lineage, we're one step closer to escaping the chains of the old microbiology.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="microbiology"></category><category term="species"></category><category term="semantics"></category><category term="rant"></category></entry><entry><title>You, Too, Can Host This Website</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/fork-this-blog.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-13T17:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-07-13:blog/fork-this-blog.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Loyal readers of this blog (of which I am sure there are exactly zero) might have noticed that things are looking a little different since yesterday. That's because I've finally developed my own &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; theme to the point that it's functional, and not too embaressing to look at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't appear &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; different—it's certainly still inspired by the &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-themes/tree/master/notmyidea-cms"&gt;sample theme&lt;/a&gt;—but now I understand 95% of the code, instead of 5%. My goal was to simplify the template files and css to the point that I could customize just about anything with a minimum of work. I also attempted to maintain compatability with all of the configuration options supported by the default theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that I know why you would want to, but you can read and copy the &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/blog"&gt;content and configuration files&lt;/a&gt; on Github. The &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/blog-theme"&gt;theme source code&lt;/a&gt; is there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By putting everything up on Github I make development easy for myself, get a free, external backup, and give off an air of open-science superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So please, fork my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="open-source"></category><category term="meta"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="website"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Even Pathogens Hate a Cheater</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/the-enemy-of-my-enemy.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-06-19T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-06-19:blog/the-enemy-of-my-enemy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I would like to apologize for the long delay since my last post. The excuse (I keep telling myself) is that, having already written too many computational articles, it was time to prove that I could write about biology too. Unfortunately I'm not nearly as good at reading the literature as I should be. Anyway, it's done. You can stop complaining now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One barrier to engineering bacteria for biofuel production or any other human endeavor is that evolutionary rates are scaled by population sizes and growth rates. For an organism with massive population sizes (trillions of individuals or more) and doubling times on the order of hours, evolution can occur quite quickly. Genetic variants within the population which are capable of growing faster will quickly take over. For an organism which is, for example, wasting a huge fraction of its energy producing your future gasoline, you can bet this months graduate stipend that mutants which put more resources into growth will sweep the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See kids, cheaters &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; win in the end! In the above example the microbes are &amp;quot;cheating&amp;quot; the metabolic engineers out of their valuable chemical products, but the same sort of evolutionary trend: favoring fitness over (and often at the expense of) any other metric we can think of, has big implications for other bacteria as well. My current research explores the impact of selection on growth rate versus resource use efficiency, but I'll write more about that some other time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many microbial populations engage in cooperative behavior. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salmonella_enterica"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Typhimurium&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, a human pathogen, uses a type III secretion system (imagine bacteria using tiny syringes to pump toxins into your cells) to induce wide-spread inflamation in the gut. By inducing enough inflamation, a population of &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; can make a niche for themselves in which they outcompete the non-pathogenic (commensal) bacteria already present. Those syringes are expensive, but without them the &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; can't colonize at all, so everyone works together for the common good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately (for &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; at least) evolution doesn't really care about the common good. Every so often a mutant will come along which has lost the type III secretion system genes, or doesn't express them as frequently or at such high levels. Since this new strain doesn't have to waste resources on producing the costly virulence factor, but can still take advantage of the inflamation being induced by all his straight-laced bretheren, he grows faster than all the normal (&amp;quot;wild-type&amp;quot;) &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt;. Even when it's almost entirely cheaters and the population's ability to inflame the host is greatly reduced, even when they're all struggling to outcompete the commensal bacteria, the mutant is still a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; better off because it's not wasting resources on that silly syringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheater wins again! In this example it's not the metabolic engineers that are being deprived of their liquid fuel, but the wild-type &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; which is being cheated out of its public resource: inflamation. Of course winning for the cheater also means that the entire population is wiped out. Without sufficient inflamation &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; can't survive, but up until that last cell is killed or expelled, at least the cheater was doing better &lt;em&gt;relative to&lt;/em&gt; the wild-type. And, in the short-term, that's what winning &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in the Game of Evolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;But wait just a minute&amp;quot;, says the astute reader, &amp;quot;why have I been cooking my eggs all these years if &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; can so easily be wiped out by this internal rebellion?&amp;quot; Aha! That's the exact question raised by Médéric Diard and co-authors in their recent paper, &amp;quot;&lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v494/n7437/abs/nature11913.html"&gt;Stabilization of cooperative virulence by the expression of an avirulent phenotype.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What they found was that wild-type &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; Typhimurium was playing chess with the mutant, sacrificing a Knight in order to take the King. Diard et al. discovered that a fraction of the wild-type Typhimurium population was not expressing the costly virulence factors. These are not cheaters; their genotype is identical to cooperators which &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; expressing the type III secretion system. Their phenotype, however, is identical to the cheaters. By choosing to not expend the energy needed for the construction of those microscopic syringes, they achieve the same fitness as the mutant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not a complete equilizer. Their daughters still have some probability of expressing the virulence factors (or else they might as well be &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; cheaters), but their fitness deficit is not as great. This boost was bought, however at the price of a reduced population size. Since only a fraction of their ranks are inducing host inflamation, the total virulence of the population is reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;But wait again&amp;quot;, you might point out, &amp;quot;just because the fitness benefit of cheating has been minimized does not mean that it has been eliminated entirely. The cheaters will still take over the population in the end, no?&amp;quot; You're right, cheaters will still grow faster in the long run, since they &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; cooperate, but &lt;strong&gt;it will require additional time for them to take over&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rate at which an allele fixes in the population is positively related to the relative fitness of that allele and therefore the cheater will not fix as quickly. In a pathogen like &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt;, the ultimate goal is to infect a new host. If the cooperators can sustain a sufficiently large population for long enough, their host is likely to pass them on to another unsuspecting (and un-hand-washing) individual. The cheater's success was all for nothing; without the type III secretion system, the mutant will never colonize another host. While they may have won the figurative battle, they lost the war. They've painted themselves into a corner. (Insert additional cliches here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diard et al., in their article, do some fantastic simulations, showing all of the dynamics at play. I encourage you to check it out. One of the most exciting sentences is the second to last (see, a snoodier blogger would have said &amp;quot;penultimate&amp;quot;), the authors point out that this tendency for mutants to out-compete the wild-type pathogen, and therefore reduce the negative effects on the host, suggests a potential &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_medicine"&gt;therapy&lt;/a&gt;: treat those suffering from &lt;em&gt;Salmonella&lt;/em&gt; with a large dose of cheaters!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="microbiology"></category><category term="cheaters"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="pathogens"></category></entry><entry><title>Compiling SciPy on RHEL6</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/scipy-on-rhel.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-20T12:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-05-20:blog/scipy-on-rhel.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Within the past two years I've discovered something interesting about myself (...actually really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; boring about myself): I can be happily entertained for hours on end setting up my computational environment &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; right. I find that it gives me a similar type of satisfaction to cataloguing my music collection. I guess you could call it a hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually this entails installing the usual suspects (&lt;code&gt;NumPy&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Pandas&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;IPython&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt;, etc.) in a python &lt;a href="http://www.virtualenv.org/en/latest/"&gt;virtual environment&lt;/a&gt;. When I'm particularly into it (which is always), I'll also compile the python distribution itself. I've had several opportunities to indulge this pasttime, most recently in setting up my research pipeline on the &lt;a href="http://cac.engin.umich.edu/resources/systems/flux"&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt; high-performance compute cluster at The University of Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing &lt;code&gt;NumPy&lt;/code&gt; is usually no trouble at all, but for some reason (if you know, please tell me), &lt;code&gt;SciPy&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; given me a &amp;quot;BlasNotFoundError&amp;quot; when installing on the Red Hat Enterprise Linux distros commonly used on academic clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; pip install scipy
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Downloading/unpacking scipy&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;  Downloading scipy-0.12.0.zip (10.2MB): 100% 10.2MB downloaded&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;numpy.distutils.system_info.BlasNotFoundError:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    Blas (http://www.netlib.org/blas/) libraries not found.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    Directories to search for the libraries can be specified in the&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    numpy/distutils/site.cfg file (section [blas]) or by setting&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    the BLAS environment variable.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; BLAS and LAPACK are installed as shared libraries: at Michigan State University I had to load the respective modules, but at UMich they're right there in &lt;code&gt;/usr/lib64/atlas&lt;/code&gt;. So why &lt;code&gt;pip install SciPy&lt;/code&gt; always gives me that error, I have no clue. I've set the BLAS and LAPACK environmental variables to the relevant shared libraries. I've run &lt;code&gt;python setup.py build --fcompiler=gnu95&lt;/code&gt; directly. But I always got that same error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; got it to work, so I thought I'd share the steps I took just in case it helps someone else. My solution was found on Stack Overflow (surprise, surprise): The accepted answer to &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/7496547/848121"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;mkdir -p ~/.local/src/
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/.local/src/
wget -O BLAS.tgz http://www.netlib.org/blas/blas.tgz
tar -xzf BLAS.tgz
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;BLAS
gfortran -O3 -std&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;legacy -m64 -fno-second-underscore -fPIC -c *.f
ar r libfblas.a *.o
ranlib libfblas.a
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;BLAS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$PWD&lt;/span&gt;/libfblas.a

&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/.local/src/
wget -O LAPACK.tgz http://www.netlib.org/lapack/lapack.tgz
tar -xzf LAPACK.tgz
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# The resulting directory may be named lapack-&amp;lt;version&amp;gt;/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# the following assumes that it&amp;#39;s named LAPACK/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;LAPACK
cp INSTALL/make.inc.gfortran make.inc
vim make.inc
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Change OPTS = -O2 to OPTS = -O2 -fPIC&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Change NOOPT = -O0 to NOOPT = -O0 -fPIC&lt;/span&gt;
make lapacklib
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;LAPACK&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$PWD&lt;/span&gt;/libflapack.a

&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/.local/src/
git clone https://github.com/scipy/scipy.git
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;scipy
python setup.py build --fcompiler gnu95
python setup.py install
&lt;span class="c"&gt;# Assuming you&amp;#39;re already in the virtualenv you want to install to.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't know which other systems this will work on, but it does successfully install SciPy for me. On Python 3.3.2, running the unit tests give me several errors and failures (nothing too scary looking), but everything passes on Python 2.7.5!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="hpc"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="scipy"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>PyMake I: Another GNU Make Clone</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/pymake-0.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-15T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-05-07:blog/pymake-0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first of two posts about my program &lt;a href="http://github.com/bsmith89/pymake/"&gt;PyMake&lt;/a&gt;. I'll post the link to Part II here when I've written it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;em&gt;While I still agree with some of the many of the views expressed in this piece, I have changed my thinking on Makefiles. I'll post a new post about the topic when I take the time to write it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an aspiring but unskilled (not yet skilled?) computer geek. You can observe this for yourself by watching me fumble my way through &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/dotfiles"&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; configuration&lt;/a&gt;, multi-threading/processing in Python, and &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; merges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely do I actually feel like my products are worth sharing with the wider world. The only reason I have a GitHub account is personal convenience and absolute confidence that no one else will ever look at it besides me. (Yes, I realize that I am invalidating the previous sentence with that glaring &amp;quot;Fork me on GitHub&amp;quot; ribbon in the top-right corner of this page. I'm putting myself out there! OKAY?!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aspiring scientist, too, I've had plenty of opportunities to practice the relevant skill sets. A laboratory rotation with &lt;a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;, and the resulting exposure to his reproducible research and &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; evangelizing, has certainly influenced the tools and techniques in my belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to use the &lt;code&gt;NumPy&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;SciPy&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Pandas&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; stack for my computational and visualization tasks. I am a relatively competent &lt;code&gt;BASH&lt;/code&gt;-ist and I work hard to write my scripts so that they'll make sense to me 5 years from now. I have even been known to do some of my data analysis in IPython notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-pipeline-is-only-sometimes-a-makefile"&gt;A Pipeline is only sometimes a Makefile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite (or maybe because of) my obsession with writing simple, reproducible pipelines, one tool I have never come to terms with is GNU &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;. While it's not quite mainstream for bioinformaticians and other computational folk, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href="http://archive.nodalpoint.org/2007/03/18/a_pipeline_is_a_makefile"&gt;promises&lt;/a&gt; to tie all those *&lt;code&gt;NIX&lt;/code&gt; style scripts together seamlessly and with built-in parallelization, selective re-running, and more, all under a declarative language syntax. I say 'promises' because, for me, it never did any of those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don't want to suggest that this ubiquitous piece of GNU software doesn't work well. I recognize that it does much of what the average user needs, but for my particular pipeline it just wasn't the right tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My problem was a seemingly simple one. I had a set of gene models (HMMs) and a set of FASTQ formatted sequences from an Illumina sequencer. The goal was to search every sample for every gene using HMMER3 and to output the results (plus a respectable amount of pre- and post-processing). The problem is, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; is designed for software compilation. Processing &lt;code&gt;foo.c&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bar.h&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;foo.o&lt;/code&gt; is easy. I, however, was asking &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; to generate the product of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; samples and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; models (&lt;strong&gt;complete aside&lt;/strong&gt;: if you're curious about how I got the &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\LaTeX$&lt;/span&gt; formatting, see &lt;a href="http://www.ceremade.dauphine.fr/~amic/blog/mathjax-and-pelican-en.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, after a dozen hours of smashing my head against the table, I was able to get my &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; to work, it required some &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; ugly tricks like secondary expansion and gratuitous calls to &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; in my macros (for others with similar problems see &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/3745177/848121"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/2880975/848121"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Plus, debugging &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; is torture, surely against the Geneva Conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to use &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;, I swear I did. It's open source, well used, extensively tested, available on all relevant systems, etc. And I probably could have... but only by keeping the ugly hack or hard-coding the recipe for each model, and that just didn't jive with my recently acquired simple/reproducible mentality. Converts always are the most zealous, afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="they-say-graduate-school-is-a-time-to-explore"&gt;They say graduate school is a time to explore&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did I do? No, I didn't immediately start writing a make replacement with all of the features I wanted like some over-eager graduate student. Jeeze! What do you people think of me!? First I checked out the &lt;a href="http://freecode.com/articles/make-alternatives"&gt;extant alternatives&lt;/a&gt;... I hated everything. So &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; I started writing a make replacement with all of the features I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result was one of the first pieces of general purpose software to come off my laptop which I wouldn't be entirely ashamed to show to an experienced programmer. It's rough, don't get me wrong, but it does everything I need and is actually kinda pretty internally. Well, at least it was before I fixed some glaring problems. Whatever. The point is I want to share &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/pymake"&gt;it&lt;/a&gt; with the world; what better stage exists for its introduction than this blog, which absolutely no one reads?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...Yeah, I'll probably post it to &lt;a href="http://reddit.com/r/python"&gt;/r/python&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tune in for Part II, in which I explain why &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; should use my software.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="development"></category><category term="make"></category><category term="pipelines"></category><category term="bioinformatics"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello World!</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/initial-commit.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-05-05T22:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-05-05:blog/initial-commit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mostly a test post and a chance to get some real content on my brand-new blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/advice-to-graduate-students.html"&gt;C. Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;'s tireless pressure to make more graduate student clones of himself—and the fact that a pretty damn good domain name was still available—I started this website/blog over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that it will turn into a place for me to share my excitement and views on microbiology, microbial ecology, mathematical ecology, bioinformatics, python, (very) amateur software development, etc. But I will be satisfied if it turns out to just be writing practice. Heaven knows I need that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you're curious, setup took me about 3 hours (plus some waiting for DNS updates). Largely, this is because I'm shamelessly mirroring Titus's well trafficked blog by using a nifty python application called &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. And at $15/year for the domain (using &lt;a href="http://hover.com"&gt;Hover&lt;/a&gt; as my registrar) and $35/year for hosting (tiny, shared server with &lt;a href="http://asmallorange.com"&gt;A Small Orange&lt;/a&gt;), I really had no financial excuse to not do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Byron&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="meta"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="website"></category><category term="hosting"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry></feed>