<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep Ecology - computation biology</title><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/feeds/tag/computation-biology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//blog.byronjsmith.com/</id><updated>2021-01-19T12:00:00-05:00</updated><subtitle>A blog of the new microbiology.</subtitle><entry><title>Things I'm Glad I Learned</title><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/things-im-glad-i-learned.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-18T18:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-19T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:blog.byronjsmith.com,2021-01-18:/things-im-glad-i-learned.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--
_(
Before starting, I've decided two things about this post that I think are
important.
(1) I'm going to publish it by 18:00 this evening,
and (2) I'll keep updating it as I think of new things to add.
)_

--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(WARNING: This post has not yet been revised. It may therefore
contain all kinds of typos, spelling errors, grammatical issues, and
delusions of wisdom, writing ability, and grandeur.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a WORK IN PROGRESS and is intended as a living document&amp;mdash;a
gratitude journal of sorts&amp;mdash;of some things that I'm glad I learned (and
often wish I had learned earlier).
I expect many of the items on this list will be relevant to computation
biology, but that may change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big idea is that there are undoubtedly things that someone will tell me
about in the coming decade that I'm going to be grateful to have learned.
This list is my chance to "pay it backwards", as it were; maybe someone
else will be grateful for something they first heard about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may also double as an inspo list for future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!--
_(
Before starting, I've decided two things about this post that I think are
important.
(1) I'm going to publish it by 18:00 this evening,
and (2) I'll keep updating it as I think of new things to add.
)_

--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(WARNING: This post has not yet been revised. It may therefore
contain all kinds of typos, spelling errors, grammatical issues, and
delusions of wisdom, writing ability, and grandeur.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is a WORK IN PROGRESS and is intended as a living document&amp;mdash;a
gratitude journal of sorts&amp;mdash;of some things that I'm glad I learned (and
often wish I had learned earlier).
I expect many of the items on this list will be relevant to computation
biology, but that may change in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big idea is that there are undoubtedly things that someone will tell me
about in the coming decade that I'm going to be grateful to have learned.
This list is my chance to "pay it backwards", as it were; maybe someone
else will be grateful for something they first heard about here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may also double as an inspo list for future posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to write a small blurb for each item, explaining what it is,
why I'm grateful for it, how it connects to other items,
when I learned about it, and who I have to thank for learning about
it originally.
Beyond that, I'll likely leave further discovery up to the reader.
I may add additional links in future edits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Computing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Dependency Graphs (e.g. GNU Make, Snakemake)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Probabilistic Programming (e.g. PyMC3, Pyro)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Containers (e.g. Docker, Singularity)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest item on this list (as of December 2020)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the Docker/Singularity combo may have finally solved all of my
software installation problems. Lol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a hard one to assign thank, because containerization has been
marketed to me by probably five different people since 2013 or so.
Very grateful that I finally picked it up in 2020!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Command-line / UNIX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm thankful that I have a glue environment, the UNIX command-line,
for all of my computational work.
Working with a command-line interace (CLI) is foundational for all of the
other headings in this "Computing" section.
I'm (as of now) not including Vim as a separate item, but it really is the
combination of Bash and (Neo)Vim that I'm most grateful for in my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure who to thank for this one. Maybe Google, because they sent me a
free Chromebook in the early days (which I used extensively for college
work until the wi-fi broke...).
It was hacking around on that Chromebook's terminal that got me into Linux,
and ultimately resulted in me replacing Windows with Ubuntu on my main laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably wouldn't be the scientist that I am now if it weren't for that
experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/519/"&gt;Relevant XKCD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything that I'm capable of programming, I'm capable of programming in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm glad that I know at least one language very well.
I think it makes me a
better teacher (of Python, but also of other languages).
I think it makes
it easier for me to learn new languages and programming concepts.
And I almost never need to decide what language to work in when I'm
doing something complicated; it's always Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for introducing me to Python goes to Dr. John Hayes, a postdoc
(neuroscientist) I worked with briefly while I was doing undergraduate research
in Margaret Saha's Lab at The College of William &amp;amp; Mary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Functional Programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a solid Haskell beginner (maybe intermediate depending on who you ask).
I don't do any of my work in Haskell (although I'm often wondering if there are
opportunites).
On the other hand, almost all of my programming is in a functional style.
I think (without any empirical evidence) I've probably saved myself a lot of
pain by (trying to):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never reuse variable names for different things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid mutation ("in the large")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use higher-level programming instead of conditionals to control program flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep side-effects away from core logic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Version Control (e.g. Git)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plain-text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Jupyter notebooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...but only for prototyping and interactive work; never for reproducible
automation.
Notebooks are a core part of my workflow, and the exploratory data analysis
phase of my work is very much done in the Jupyter environment.
On the other hand, my love of workflow managers like Snakemake means that
I try to keep interactive work at the "tips" of my data processing DAG.
Notebooks are a great place to do prototyping, but the second I need the
resulting data for a downstream step it's probably time to convert it to a
script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Biology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Organic Chemistry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think having first-principles knowledge about how biology is built out of
chemistry has served me very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure there's much more for me to say than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Neutral Evolution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything is adaptive (e.g. I'm 99% sure eye color doesn't affect survival
or reproduction.)
It's incredibly infuriating to see so many Appeals to Natural Selection
(a new logical fallacy I'm naming here first, 2021-01-18) in our
general discourse.
To my eye, it's all B.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introduced to me by/on: unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Spandrils&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything that seems adaptive, even when there's evidence for convergent
evolution, actually is.
Some traits are a natural consequence of physical reality.
This is important to more than just snails;
it's probably a part of the answer to e.g. "why do animals have such fancy
microbiomes?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to guess, I learned about spandrils first in my evolutionary biology
class in college.
I'm sure I can figure out who taught that class if I dig into my emails,
but I'm going to put that off for another day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Microbial Communities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no doubt that the research I did in high school with Dr. May Voytek at
the USGS (in 2006 and 2007) was one of the most important experiences for my
career development.
I was enthralled then&amp;mdash;as I am now&amp;mdash;with the ways in which microbial
metabolisms can combine in complex communities to perform immensely important
processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Graphical Models&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My introduction to graphical models was really an introduction to maximum
likelihood estimation and structural equation modeling taught by Colin Kremer
and TODO during two sessions of ELME ("Enhanced Linkages between Mathematics and Ecology")
at Kellogg Biological Station in the summer of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bayesian Statistics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not the elegance of Bayes's Rule that I'm enamoured with;
it's how Bayesian statistics &lt;em&gt;democratizes&lt;/em&gt; inference (e.g. the Inference
Button).
If you have a data generating model and some data, you can make
logically consistent statements about it's parameters.
&lt;em&gt;And&lt;/em&gt; you get propagation of uncertainty for free!
How cool is that??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first material impact on my understanding of Bayesian stats
was probably in Statistics for Ecologists (was that the name?),
taught by Dr. Ian Dworkin at Michigan State University.
ELME also played a key role in me picking up what Dr. Dworkin was putting
down, although I still only got a whiff of the importance.
It was probably another 4+ years before I learned enough basics to
start calling myself a Bayesian (see PyMC3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Causal Inference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teaching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning Objectives / Concept Inventories&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Flipped Classroom&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Expert Bias&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning By Teaching&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me (and undoubtedly many other people to), I learn something the best
when I have to teach it.
This served me very well during my undergraduate genetics class when
Nishant Kishore and I would cram the night before a test by me "teaching" him
the material to the extent that I had understood it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This compounds with other ideas in pedagogy, like Expert Bias and flipped
classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Growth Mindset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It feels incredibly powerful to see ones current self as just a single stage
in the development of their full capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I really first learned this in Multivariate Calculus my sophomore
year; I distinctly remember how gratifying it was to go from absolutely zero
understanding to a B-minus on the final; a bad grade relative to my other
classes but I'm very proud of it nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Deficit Model of Persuasion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who disagree with you about the way the world works often have all the
same facts as you do.
We don't convince people of our world view by giving them more facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this depressing. But on the flip side you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be much more effective
at persuasion by doing two key things (to my limited understanding):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share your emotional reasons for your beliefs
  (e.g. I'm super &lt;strong&gt;excited&lt;/strong&gt; to be able to travel and hug my parents again
  after they and I are vaccinated.
  I've been &lt;strong&gt;scared&lt;/strong&gt; about their safety, and vaccination feels like an
  opportunity for &lt;strong&gt;optimism&lt;/strong&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate that their community shares that belief.
  This is usually done by making them part of &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; community.
  (I think it's really great that our family/college/neighborhood has really
  come together to get everyone vaccinated.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obviously key for science communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Privelege&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing my advantages has been really helpful in building empathy for
disadvantaged groups in the world.
I want everyone to have the same access and opportunities for success and
contribution that I have had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably internalized this sense circa 2015...ish.
Not sure if there's any one person to thank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Talking About Yourself (e.g. "I feel..." Language)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that my interpersonal relationships have been bolstered by
a mutual ability to focus what we say on &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; needs and feelings instead
of claiming some objective sense of reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can say with some certainty that communication is much more likely to
transition into a fight (not communication) when I break this rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Cognitive Biases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially the "Fundamental Attribution Error".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly because I am also subject to all of the same biases, but also
because it helps me to understand peoples' behavior, even at large scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Profit and Monopoly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I have a hobbiest's understanding of economic theory.
As I understand it, in an idealized world (perfect market efficiency) no
producer should be able to make a marginal profit in the long run.
Obviously this is not really the case, since e.g. doctors are making
great money for their time.
I think it's fascinating that in many (most?) cases where value is being
captured by a small group of people this can be assigned to some sort of
monopoly power.
For instance doctors have the AMA controlling the supply of medical labor,
Genentech has various patents and corporate secrets, and ISPs have
both cartel power and huge barriers to entry in most regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monopolies aren't all evil (left as an exercise to the reader).
Appropriately regulating these monopolies seems like a key
role of governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Intentional Communities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this millenium, many people (including me) are suffering from less community
than the previous one.
This would appear to be due to geographic mobility (loss of family and
friends), secularization, an extended youth, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it has been empowering to realize that we can choose to have those
communities if we're willing to work for it.
Intentional communities (a.k.a. communes, kibbutzim) prove it, and give me
something to aspire to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting Things Done (GTD)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't actually use the GTD system, so &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Rituals&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="Misc."></category><category term="education"></category><category term="open science"></category><category term="computation biology"></category><category term="biology"></category><category term="snakemake"></category><category term="make"></category><category term="pymc3"></category><category term="bayesian"></category></entry></feed>