<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep Ecology - development</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/feeds/tag/development.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2016-03-04T10:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>PyMake I: Another GNU Make clone</title><link href="http://bsmith89.github.io/blog/pymake-0.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-07T19:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-03-04T10:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:bsmith89.github.io,2013-05-07:blog/pymake-0.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;(Edit 1): &lt;del&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first of two posts about my program &lt;a href="http://github.com/bsmith89/pymake/"&gt;PyMake&lt;/a&gt;. I'll post the link to Part II here when I've written it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;em&gt;While I still agree with some of the many of the views expressed in this piece, I have changed my thinking on Makefiles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Edit 2): &lt;del&gt;&lt;em&gt;I'll post a new post about the topic when I take the time to write it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;em&gt;I've written a &lt;a href="make-analysis.html"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on using &lt;em&gt;Make&lt;/em&gt; for reproducible data analysis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an aspiring but unskilled (not yet skilled?) computer geek. You can observe this for yourself by watching me fumble my way through &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/dotfiles"&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt; configuration&lt;/a&gt;, multi-threading/processing in Python, and &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; merges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely do I actually feel like my products are worth sharing with the wider world. The only reason I have a GitHub account is personal convenience and absolute confidence that no one else will ever look at it besides me. (Yes, I realize that I am invalidating the previous sentence with that glaring &amp;quot;Fork me on GitHub&amp;quot; ribbon in the top-right corner of this page. I'm putting myself out there! OKAY?!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aspiring scientist, too, I've had plenty of opportunities to practice the relevant skill sets. A laboratory rotation with &lt;a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/"&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt;, and the resulting exposure to his reproducible research and &lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; evangelizing, has certainly influenced the tools and techniques in my belt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to use the &lt;code&gt;NumPy&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;SciPy&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;Pandas&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;matplotlib&lt;/code&gt; stack for my computational and visualization tasks. I am a relatively competent &lt;code&gt;BASH&lt;/code&gt;-ist and I work hard to write my scripts so that they'll make sense to me 5 years from now. I have even been known to do some of my data analysis in IPython notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="a-pipeline-is-only-sometimes-a-makefile"&gt;A Pipeline is only sometimes a Makefile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite (or maybe because of) my obsession with writing simple, reproducible pipelines, one tool I have never come to terms with is GNU &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;. While it's not quite mainstream for bioinformaticians and other computational folk, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href="http://archive.nodalpoint.org/2007/03/18/a_pipeline_is_a_makefile"&gt;promises&lt;/a&gt; to tie all those *&lt;code&gt;NIX&lt;/code&gt; style scripts together seamlessly and with built-in parallelization, selective re-running, and more, all under a declarative language syntax. I say 'promises' because, for me, it never did any of those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don't want to suggest that this ubiquitous piece of GNU software doesn't work well. I recognize that it does much of what the average user needs, but for my particular pipeline it just wasn't the right tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My problem was a seemingly simple one. I had a set of gene models (HMMs) and a set of FASTQ formatted sequences from an Illumina sequencer. The goal was to search every sample for every gene using HMMER3 and to output the results (plus a respectable amount of pre- and post-processing). The problem is, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; is designed for software compilation. Processing &lt;code&gt;foo.c&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bar.h&lt;/code&gt; into &lt;code&gt;foo.o&lt;/code&gt; is easy. I, however, was asking &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; to generate the product of &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; samples and &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;&lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; models (&lt;strong&gt;complete aside&lt;/strong&gt;: if you're curious about how I got the &lt;span class="math inline"&gt;$\LaTeX$&lt;/span&gt; formatting, see &lt;a href="http://www.ceremade.dauphine.fr/~amic/blog/mathjax-and-pelican-en.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While, after a dozen hours of smashing my head against the table, I was able to get my &lt;code&gt;Makefile&lt;/code&gt; to work, it required some &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; ugly tricks like secondary expansion and gratuitous calls to &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; in my macros (for others with similar problems see &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/3745177/848121"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/2880975/848121"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Plus, debugging &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; is torture, surely against the Geneva Conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to use &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;, I swear I did. It's open source, well used, extensively tested, available on all relevant systems, etc. And I probably could have... but only by keeping the ugly hack or hard-coding the recipe for each model, and that just didn't jive with my recently acquired simple/reproducible mentality. Converts always are the most zealous, afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="they-say-graduate-school-is-a-time-to-explore"&gt;They say graduate school is a time to explore&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did I do? No, I didn't immediately start writing a make replacement with all of the features I wanted like some over-eager graduate student. Jeeze! What do you people think of me!? First I checked out the &lt;a href="http://freecode.com/articles/make-alternatives"&gt;extant alternatives&lt;/a&gt;... I hated everything. So &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; I started writing a make replacement with all of the features I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result was one of the first pieces of general purpose software to come off my laptop which I wouldn't be entirely ashamed to show to an experienced programmer. It's rough, don't get me wrong, but it does everything I need and is actually kinda pretty internally. Well, at least it was before I fixed some glaring problems. Whatever. The point is I want to share &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/pymake"&gt;it&lt;/a&gt; with the world; what better stage exists for its introduction than this blog, which absolutely no one reads?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...Yeah, I'll probably post it to &lt;a href="http://reddit.com/r/python"&gt;/r/python&lt;/a&gt; too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tune in for Part II, in which I explain why &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; should use my software.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="python"></category><category term="software"></category><category term="development"></category><category term="make"></category><category term="pipelines"></category><category term="bioinformatics"></category></entry></feed>