<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Deep Ecology - microbiome</title><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/feeds/tag/microbiome.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>//blog.byronjsmith.com/</id><updated>2019-06-20T15:00:00-04:00</updated><subtitle>A blog of the new microbiology.</subtitle><entry><title>Changes to the gut microbiome resulting from acarbose treatment are associated with increased longevity in mice</title><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/acarbose-longevity-preprint.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-01T12:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-20T15:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:blog.byronjsmith.com,2018-05-01:/acarbose-longevity-preprint.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!--
## Introduction
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I'm excited to announce that we've posted a
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/311456"&gt;preprint of our latest manuscript to the bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;,
as well as submitted it for peer review to the open access journal Microbiome.
I'll update this note if and when it gets accepted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit 2019-06-20: Our submission to Microbiome was tranferred to BMC
Microbiology, and was finally accepted (more than a full year in review!).
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-019-1494-7"&gt;Check it out in print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days it seems like the only research more over-hyped than
"microbiome" is &lt;em&gt;longevity-enhancement&lt;/em&gt;.
It is therefore with some trepidation that I have released into this world of
buzz the first chapter of my dissertation, titled:
"Changes in the gut microbiota and fermentation products associated with
enhanced longevity in acarbose-treated mice."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous work (done by my co-authors on this paper as well as others) has
conclusively demonstrated that treatment with the anti-diabetic drug acarbose
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.12170"&gt;substantially increases lifespan in mice&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.12496"&gt;also&lt;/a&gt;).
The magnitude of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!--
## Introduction
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I'm excited to announce that we've posted a
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/311456"&gt;preprint of our latest manuscript to the bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;,
as well as submitted it for peer review to the open access journal Microbiome.
I'll update this note if and when it gets accepted.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit 2019-06-20: Our submission to Microbiome was tranferred to BMC
Microbiology, and was finally accepted (more than a full year in review!).
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12866-019-1494-7"&gt;Check it out in print&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days it seems like the only research more over-hyped than
"microbiome" is &lt;em&gt;longevity-enhancement&lt;/em&gt;.
It is therefore with some trepidation that I have released into this world of
buzz the first chapter of my dissertation, titled:
"Changes in the gut microbiota and fermentation products associated with
enhanced longevity in acarbose-treated mice."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous work (done by my co-authors on this paper as well as others) has
conclusively demonstrated that treatment with the anti-diabetic drug acarbose
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.12170"&gt;substantially increases lifespan in mice&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/acel.12496"&gt;also&lt;/a&gt;).
The magnitude of the effect in males&amp;mdash;where it's the most
pronounced&amp;mdash;puts it on par with rapamycin and 17-&amp;alpha;-estradiol, two
drugs that have gotten heavy interest from the longevity-enhancement crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
TODO: Link to this buzz.
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the approximately 20% increase in median lifespan in males is not as big
as dietary restriction (a whopping ~40% in several studies), and the effect
is much less in females (only 5% give-or-take) this still represents an
exciting potential therapy if it can be reproduced in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, it represents another tiny toehold in the still inscrutable
field of longevity science.
(Disclaimer: &lt;em&gt;I am not a longevity expert.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To drive home how little we understand about longevity, not only do we have
just a rudimentary understanding of
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2015.02.020"&gt;how dietary restriction increases lifespan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:dr-mechanism-note"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:dr-mechanism-note"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;,
but we can't even say if acarbose (or any other therapy) has a similar
mechanism of action.
It seems reasonable to expect that it might;
acarbose inhibits the enzymes that break down starch, reducing the uptake of
glucose after a meal.
However, the physiological response to long-term treatment with the drug is
quite distinct from dietary restriction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrepancy has inspired an alternative hypothesis: looking instead to the
starch left undigested and that therefore enters the &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; digestive system
in much larger amounts.
If this increased supply of substrate for microbial fermentation causes an
increased production of "good" bacterial products&amp;mdash;for instance short-chain
fatty acids (SCFAs)&amp;mdash;then this could result in improved health and,
ultimately, longevity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Concept diagram: our alternative model for acarbose's effect on longevity.
" src="//blog.byronjsmith.com/static/images/longev_concept.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Features and limitations of our study&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explore this hypothesis, we have been very fortunate to collaborate
with the National Institute on Aging's
&lt;a href="https://www.nia.nih.gov/research/dab/interventions-testing-program-itp"&gt;Interventions Testing Program (ITP)&lt;/a&gt;, an
ongoing multi-institutional study that trials promising anti-aging therapies
in large mouse cohorts.
The life-extending properties of acarbose were first observed in this study,
and subsequent mouse cohorts have both confirmed the original finding and built
on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My manuscript is based on the analysis of fecal samples from these mice,
measuring the concentrations of three key SCFAs and other metabolites as
well as the composition of the bacterial community.
Longevity studies like these are challenging simply because you're waiting
for your mice to die naturally.
This is both time consuming and expensive;
you need quite a few mice for statistical reasons, and they can live for years.
To my knowledge, ours is the first study to combine characterization of the
fecal microbiome with longevity measurement in normal, healthy mice.
Another valuable feature of our study is the pairing of chemical analysis with
community characterization in the same samples, presumably improving
our ability to detect associations between bacterial taxa and their
fermentation products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, as with any research this study has crucial limitations
and is only the first step in process of validating an exciting
hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we did not set out to test the central, causal claim of our model:
    that SCFAs in the gut increase lifespan.
    To do so would require experimental control of one or more of the three key
    SCFAs in the lower digestive system&amp;mdash;acetate, butyrate and
    propionate&amp;mdash;&lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; independently affecting mouse physiology.
    While a useful manipulation, acarbose supplementation has other major
    effects (on blood glucose, for instance) and therefore does not qualify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, by definition, the mice for which we obtained fecal pellets had
    survived up to the time of collection.
    Since samples were collected from mice nearing to the median lifespan of
    the control mice,
    our interpretation are therefore limited to &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; mice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, this was a purely cross-sectional study with a single sample
    collected from each mouse.
    We can answer the most pressing questions without longitudinal sampling,
    but variation within each mouse, on the time-scale of hours, days, or
    weeks, surely introduced noise and decreased our statistical power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we only measure chemical and community composition in &lt;em&gt;feces&lt;/em&gt;.
    While this is an effective proxy for the gut microbiome, and a huge
    fraction of studies accept this shortcoming, it is important to remember
    that fecal SCFA concentrations may not reflect bacterial production, nor
    exposure of the gut and other host tissues to these compounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting findings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study explores predictions of the hypothesis that acarbose
increases longevity via the bacterial production of short-chain fatty acids,
finding that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;acarbose treatment modifies the composition of the gut microbiota,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;variation in the abundance of particular bacterial community members
is associated with variation in the concentration of fermentation products,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one or more of the major SCFAs are increased in the feces of acarbose
treated mice, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SCFA concentrations are associated with mouse lifespan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While our model does not supersede the more mainstream hypothesis that
acarbose acts to increase longevity through its effects on glucose homeostasis
pathways, our work is important support for an alternative model in which the
microbiota plays a central role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know all the juicy details, &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1101/311456"&gt;read the paper&lt;/a&gt;.
Here, however, I want to expand a little bit on some
of the less obvious bits that I think are worth your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Quantification of bacterial density&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting methodological feature of our 16S rRNA gene survey is the
inclusion of an internal DNA standard for the purpose of comparing the absolute
abundance of the bacterial population between samples.
This approach has been published in the past (&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s40168-016-0175-0"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.soilbio.2016.02.003"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), but is not widely implemented.
Normally, sequence based surveys of bacterial communities are limited to
comparing the relative abundance of particular amplicons.
By spiking in a known amount of defined DNA&amp;mdash;in this case
10 &amp;mu;L of a stationary phase culture of &lt;em&gt;Sphingopyxis alaskensis&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;we
can compare population density of bacteria per gram of feces
based on the recovery rate of the exogenous 16S gene.
Since we can uniquely identify and remove the foreign sequence,
this approach is fully complementary to a relative-abundance based analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use this tool to confirm that observed increases in the relative abundance
of several taxa reflect increases in their population size, rather than
the decreased abundance of other bacteria, a distinction that is impossible
to make with standard survey methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study we did not attempt to quantify the density of bacteria in the
spike itself, which means that our abundance estimates are in units of
spike-equivalents rather than gene copies.
This does not affect our interpretations, although it can create challenges for
communication.
We skipped this step because it is probably not possible to accurately estimate
cell counts in the endemic community based on 16S rRNA gene density.
Extraction and amplification efficiency, as well as
&lt;a href="https://rrndb.umms.med.umich.edu/"&gt;16S rRNA gene copies per cell&lt;/a&gt;, vary among species.
Instead we depend on an assumption of per cell copy number invariance in the
community on average, as well as in the specific taxa being assessed.
For this reason, we've opted to use "spike-adjusted abundance" as a euphemism
for the estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to write more about this approach in the future.
For now I'll just say it was a small, but valuable feature of our study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Identification of bacterial function&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting method that I'm proud to have included was a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lasso_(statistics)"&gt;LASSO regression&lt;/a&gt; of metabolite concentrations on taxon abundances.
Our reason for doing this was the belief that the bacteria
most strongly correlated with particular fermentation products were the most
likely to be producing them.
This na&amp;iuml;ve approach appears to have paid off;
the method identified contenders for these functional roles that, in many
cases, match &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; expectations.
For instance, the most abundant &lt;em&gt;Lactobacillus&lt;/em&gt; was closely associated with
lactate concentrations.
(Surprised?)
Likewise, the dominant members of the &lt;em&gt;Muribaculaceae&lt;/em&gt; appear
to be predictive of propionate concentrations, matching functional annotations
of genomes from this family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are almost certainly better methods for discovering the taxa that
produce particular metabolites,
but LASSO regression is a surprisingly simple approach and sufficient to
demonstrate a relationship between bacterial abundances and SCFAs,
while being (theoretically) more robust to other sources of co-linearity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A reproducible paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the joy of having contributed to SCIENCE,
I am also proud to declare that the results&lt;sup id="fnref:but-one"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:but-one"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in our manuscript
are recreate-able by sufficiently interested readers.
Raw sequence data are available from the &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/PRJNA448009"&gt;SRA&lt;/a&gt;, and everything
else&amp;mdash;HPLC peak area tables, mouse survival data, and all of the relevant
metadata&amp;mdash;can be found in a &lt;a href="https://github.com/bsmith89/smith2018paper"&gt;public GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.
That repo also comes with all of the pipeline
code, implemented as scripts and a Makefile, for raw data
processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone who doesn't want to install a bunch of software and
reserve about a hundred hours of CPU time
to reprocess our sequences, intermediate results are available in a preloaded
SQLite database.
Finally, Jupyter notebooks with code to reproduce published figures and
statistics have also been included.
I'm not providing a prepared container, unfortunately, and some of the
required software can be challenging to install.
Once that's done, though, the Makefile is designed to generate the finished
paper with a single invocation of &lt;code&gt;make paper&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there's an "official", current release of that repository,
&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1229203"&gt;checkpointed by Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;,
I may implement patches if they make results easier for readers to recreate.
If anyone out there wants to get really crazy, I'll even take pull-requests!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This manuscript is a key chapter of my PhD thesis, and I'll be building off of
the findings in subsequent work.
So stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Run the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:dr-mechanism-note"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quote: "The mechanisms mediating the health benefits of
  DR are not fully understood in any organism."&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:dr-mechanism-note" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:but-one"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except for one: Our supplemental materials do not included the code
        needed to recreate the first figure, survival curves demonstrating
        that the population of mice from which we sampled recapitulate the
        sex-specific longevity effects of acarbose.
        This result was computed by a collaborator and uses longevity data
        that will be released with a different paper, currently in
        preparation.
        I believe that this particular result is a relatively minor part
        of our story, confirming a previously observed, and well
        established, pattern.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:but-one" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Biology"></category><category term="microbiome"></category><category term="acarbose"></category><category term="preprint"></category><category term="SCFAs"></category><category term="longevity"></category><category term="open science"></category></entry><entry><title>Not all carbs are bad</title><link href="//blog.byronjsmith.com/fiber-butyrate-life.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-27T21:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-10-27T21:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Byron J. Smith</name></author><id>tag:blog.byronjsmith.com,2015-10-27:/fiber-butyrate-life.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This brief post was written as a popular science article for a class on
science communication.
My own research is currently focused on exactly this topic: describing microbial
community dynamics associated with acarbose treatment and the production of
butyrate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick internet search search for “low-carb diets” comes back filled with
promises to make you sleek, spry, and slim just by cutting out this entire
category of foods.
The popularity of these diets shouldn't surprise you.
Recent research has implicated overconsumption of sugars, the simplest form
of carbohydrates, and starchy foods, which can quickly be broken down into
sugars, in the increased risk of heart disease, obesity, even some forms of
dementia.
Americans have responded quickly, with 50% trying to limit their intake of
sugars and carbohydrates according to a &lt;a href="http://www.foodinsight.org/sites/default/files/FINAL%202014%20Food%20and%20Health%20Survey%20Executive%20Summary_0.pdf)."&gt;2014 survey&lt;/a&gt;.
That same survey found only 74% of respondents believe that a healthy diet
can include moderate amounts of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This brief post was written as a popular science article for a class on
science communication.
My own research is currently focused on exactly this topic: describing microbial
community dynamics associated with acarbose treatment and the production of
butyrate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick internet search search for “low-carb diets” comes back filled with
promises to make you sleek, spry, and slim just by cutting out this entire
category of foods.
The popularity of these diets shouldn't surprise you.
Recent research has implicated overconsumption of sugars, the simplest form
of carbohydrates, and starchy foods, which can quickly be broken down into
sugars, in the increased risk of heart disease, obesity, even some forms of
dementia.
Americans have responded quickly, with 50% trying to limit their intake of
sugars and carbohydrates according to a &lt;a href="http://www.foodinsight.org/sites/default/files/FINAL%202014%20Food%20and%20Health%20Survey%20Executive%20Summary_0.pdf)."&gt;2014 survey&lt;/a&gt;.
That same survey found only 74% of respondents believe that a healthy diet
can include moderate amounts of sugar, down from 84% in 2013.
If these trends lead to decreasing calorie consumption as a whole, we could
see a decline in obesity, diabetes, and heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there may be an unintended consequence of these quickly
shifting attitudes.
The fraction of Americans that are actively trying to consume fiber and whole
grains in their diet dropped to 53% in 2014 from 62% the year before.
Dietary fiber is also a carbohydrate, made-up of individual sugars combined
like daisies into long chains and branching structures.
What makes these carbohydrates special is that, due to the links holding them
together, the human body is not capable of breaking fiber down into
individual sugars to be absorbed into the blood stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without any way to digest it, fiber is often thought of as an inert component
of our food, increasing feelings of fullness but not contributing to the
calorie content, all while improving our digestive health by absorbing water
and pushing everything smoothly along.
While some of the benefits of fiber consumption may be due to its inertness,
the problem with that description is that it entirely ignores the multitudes
of microbes living in our gut, collectively referred to as the microbiome.
Many of these bacteria can break down and feed on dietary fibers, in the
process, producing a huge variety of byproducts.
The discomfort and flatulence associated with the consumption of beans, for
instance&amp;mdash;or in lactose intolerant individuals, milk&amp;mdash;is due to the
carbon dioxide and hydrogen gas belched out by trillions of microbes in the
large intestine while they feast on carbohydrates inaccessible to our bodies.
Despite the discomfort, the breakdown of these compounds by fermentation
produces a number of small molecules called short-chain fatty acids, each of
which you can already recognize by smell: acetate (the acid in vinegar),
lactate (which gives cheese its sharpness), propionate (similar to body
odor), and butyrate (the distinctive stink of vomit).
Despite its odious stench, butyrate has a number of
&lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2036.2007.03562.x"&gt;health benefits&lt;/a&gt;, notably its ability to reduce
inflammation, a fact that should come as welcome news to the almost
&lt;a href="http://www.ccfa.org/assets/pdfs/updatedibdfactbook.pdf"&gt;2 million&lt;/a&gt; Americans who suffer from inflammatory bowel diseases.
The ability of these fibers to stimulate the growth of certain beneficial gut
bacteria puts them into the category of dietary supplements called
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prebiotic_(nutrition)"&gt;"prebiotics"&lt;/a&gt; (rather than probiotics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, diabetics have been prescribed a drug called acarbose to temper
the glucose spikes that occur after starch-heavy meals.
Acarbose operates by blocking the breakdown and absorption of starch,
effectively (and unintentionally) transforming it into dietary fiber to be
broken down by the bacteria in our gut.
Unsurprisingly, flatulence and diarrhea are commonly reported side effects.
A little discomfort might be worth it, though, if the &lt;a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/acel.12170"&gt;finding&lt;/a&gt;
that treatment with acarbose extends lifespan in mice&amp;mdash;by as much as
20%&amp;mdash;applies to humans as well.
Why it has this effect is unclear, but if it is due to the increased
production of butyrate by gut bacteria, increased fiber consumption could
have similar effects.
Studies are currently underway testing the longevity effects of inulin, a
dietary fiber from chicory root.
If this and other fibers also increase lifespan in mice, butyrate, and by
extension the microbiome, will be new targets for the growing field of
life-extending therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Biology"></category><category term="longevity"></category><category term="microbiome"></category><category term="diet"></category><category term="popular science"></category></entry></feed>